

Beirut, Lebanon

🛘 (+961) 71-778924 | 🗷 wissam.antoun@gmail.com | 🤻 wissamantoun.github.io | 🗖 wissamantoun | 🎓 Wissam Antoun

## Summary \_\_

I'm an Artificial Intelligence and Machine Learning Scientist specialized in state-of-the-art Natural Language Processing (NLP) techniques. My research focuses mainly on language modeling, conversational agents and on the intersection of NLP and Information Retrieval. The output of my 2 years of Master's research includes 7 peer-reviewed papers published in top NLP conferences and a nomination for the Abdul Hadi Debs Endowment Award for Academic Excellence.

I recently ranked first among 74 teams in the largest Arabic Sentiment Analysis competition. Moreover, I have been reviewing papers for international peer-reviewed journals and venues in the AI and NLP domain. I gave multiple NLP workshops as an AI instructor at Zaka, in addition to my teaching experience that i gained as a teaching assistant at the American University of Beirut. I'm currently a Data Scientist at Siren Analytics, making use of my Al/NLP skills to solve various problems that directly impacts the public sector.

# **Education**

### **Masters Of Engineering In Electrical And Computer Engineering**

Beirut, Lebanon

AMERICAN UNIVERSITY OF BEIRUT

Feb. 2018 - Sep. 2020

- · Major Area: Artificial Intelligence and Machine Learning systems
- · Minro Area: Software, Networking and Security
- · Awarded Graduate Fellowship with full tuition coverage
- · Nominated for the Abdul Hadi Debs Endowment Award for Academic Excellence

#### **Bachelor Of Engineering In Computer And Communication Engineering**

Zouk Mosbeh, Lebanon

NOTRE DAME UNIVERSITY - LOUAIZE Sept. 2014 - Jul. 2017

• GPA: 3.58 Dean's List for 6 semesters

# Work Experience \_\_\_\_\_

**Siren Analytics** Beirut, Lebanon

DATA SCIENTIST

Jan. 2021 - Current

· Worked on information retrieval, search engines, named-entity recognition, face-recognition, optical character recognition, anomaly detection systems for lockdown mobility permits, and data analysis as part of an effort to create the first e-gov platform in lebanon.

#### **MIND Lab - American University of Beirut**

Beirut, Lebanon Sep. 2018 - Jan. 2021

GRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANT

- Co-founded AUB's Machine INtelligence Development Lab
- My research focused on state-of-the-art NLP technologies for natural language understanding, generation, and chatbots.
- · Worked on pre-training various Arabic language models that ranges from RNN-based to the Transformer-based models, using Cloud TPU and **GPU** instances
- · Researched improving temporal and spacial resolution of remote sensing ML systems for soil moisture prediction.

#### **ECE Dept. - American University of Beirut**

Feb. 2018 - Dec. 2020

GRADUATE TEACHING ASSISTANT

• EECE 435L: Software Tools Lab, Co-Instructor (3 semesters). Delivered a range of teaching and assessment activities including tutorials directed

- towards the delivery of modern Software Tools at the undergraduate level.
- EECE 696: Applied Parallel Programming, Lab instructor (1 semester). Delivered hands-on experience to graduate students on parallel programming and GPU computing using the CUDA C/C++ framework on local computers and on AWS. • EECE 330: Data Structures and Algorithms, Lab instructor (1 semester). Delivered hands-on experience on fundamental algorithms and data
- structures used in software applications at the undergraduate level using C++.
- Introduced a plagiarism detection tool for computer code to the Electrical Engineering Department.

#### **Academic Reviewer**

REVIEWER FOR THE FOLLOWING JOURNALS:

2020 - Current

- Journal of King Saud University Computer and Information Sciences (IF: 13.47)
- Expert Systems with Applications (IF: 6.95)
- Workshop on Arabic Natural Language Processing (h-index: 51, i10-index: 50)
- ACM Transactions on Asian and Low-Resource Language Information Processing TALLIP (IF: 1.42)
- Language Resources and Evaluation (IF: 1.36)

OCTOBER 12, 2021 WISSAM ANTOUN · RÉSUMÉ **Zaka** Online

Al Instructor May. 2020

• Gave a 4-part online workshop series titled *A Comprehensive NLP series* that was focused on delivering the major NLP concepts through handson coding examples along with the NLP fundamentals theory.

Stars of Science Doha, Qatar

MACHINE LEARNING EXPERT

Feb. 2020 - Apr. 2020

• Provided Machine Learning and Artificial Intelligence solutions as part of the support team that helps contestants throughout their Stars of Science journey

### Huawei Technologies (Lebanon) S.A.R.L.

Beirut, Lebanon

2019 **Cited by: 10** 

INTERN

June 2016 - Aug. 2016

• Learned about various LTE principles, base station hardware, and Microwave transmissions systems.

### Honors & Awards \_\_\_\_\_

#### INTERNATIONAL

2021	<b>First Place</b> , Arabic Sentiment Analysis 2021 @ KAUST (wti.kaust.edu.sa/solve/Arabic-Sentiment-Analysis-Challenge)	Kaggle, Online
2020	Second Place, OSACT4-Shared task on Offensive Language Detection	Marseille, France
2019	Best Domain Detection system, Qatar International Fake News Detection and Annotation Contest	Doha, Qatar

#### DOMESTIC

2021	Nominee, Abdul Hadi Debs Endowment Award for Academic Excellence	AUB, Lebanon
2019	<b>Second Place</b> , Mindsets-OLX Datathon, Best car price prediction score.(www.kaggle.com/c/mindsets)	AUB, Lebanon
2019	First place, Big Data, AI, and Media Hackathon Powered by Touch and Anghami	AUB, Lebanon

## **Publications**

My full publication list with links and up-to-date citation scores is available on my Google Scholar page (linked above).

My Research metrics:

A Comprehensive Approach for A Smart Medication Dispenser

International Journal of Computing and Digital Systems, University of Bahrain

Kassem, Abdallah, Wissam Antoun, Mustapha Hamad, and Chady El-Moucary

My Research metrics:	
Citation score: 261	
• h-index: 6	
• i10-index: 5	
AraGPT2: Pre-Trained Transformer for Arabic Language Generation  Antoun, Wissam, Fady Baly, and Hazem Hajj	2021
Proceedings of the Sixth Arabic Natural Language Processing Workshop co-located with EACL, Kyiv, Ukraine	Cited by: 6
AraELECTRA: Pre-Training Text Discriminators for Arabic Language Understanding	
Antoun, Wissam, Fady Baly, and Hazem Hajj	2021
Proceedings of the Sixth Arabic Natural Language Processing Workshop co-located with EACL, Kyiv, Ukraine	Cited by: 6
Empathetic BERT2BERT Conversational Model: Learning Arabic Language Generation with little data	0001
Naous, Tarek, <b>Wissam Antoun</b> , Reem Mahmoud, and Hazem Hajj	2021
Proceedings of the Sixth Arabic Natural Language Processing Workshop co-located with EACL, Kyiv, Ukraine	Cited by: 1
AraBERT: Transformer-based Model for Arabic Language Understanding	
Antoun, Wissam, Fady Baly, and Hazem Hajj	2020
Proceedings of the 4th Workshop on Open-Source Arabic Corpora and Processing Tools co-located with LREC 2020, Marseille, France	Cited by: 177
Multi-Task Learning using AraBert for Offensive Language Detection	
Djandji, Marc, Fady Baly, <b>Wissam Antoun</b> , and Hazem Hajj	2020
Proceedings of the 4th Workshop on Open-Source Arabic Corpora and Processing Tools co-located with LREC, Marseille, France	Cited by: 11
State of the Art Models for Fake News Detection Tasks	
<b>Antoun</b> , <b>Wissam</b> , Fady Baly, Rim Achour, Amir Hussein, and Hazem Hajj	2020
2020 IEEE International Conference on Informatics, IoT, and Enabling Technologies (ICIoT'2020), Doha, Qatar	Cited by: 8
hULMonA: The Universal Language Model in Arabic	
ElJundi, Obeida, <b>Wissam Antoun</b> , Nour El Droubi, Hazem Hajj, Wassim El-Hajj, and Khaled Shaban	2019
Proceedings of the Fourth Arabic Natural Language Processing Workshop co-located with ACL, Florence, Italy	Cited by: 26
Real-Time Fire Detection Using CUDA (Poster)	
Antoun, Wissam and Manal Jalloul	2019
ISC High Performance, Frankfurt, Germany	Cited by: 1

2018 Cited by: 15

## **Presentations**

### AraBERT: pretraining, use cases and future improvements

Online

PyData Khobar and KSU's IWAN Research Group Meetups

May. 2020

· Introduced the AraBERT model for the Arab community and explained the pretraining and fine-tuning procedure

### High Performance Computing for Lebanon (HPC4L) Brown Bag

AUB, Lebanon

PRESENTER FOR CURRENT AND FUTURE/POTENTIAL USE CASES FOR HPC4L

Feb. 2020

- Introduced the use case of HPC for pretraining transformer-based model for Arabic language Understanding
- Explained parallelization and scaling techniques for transformer models

## Skills

Python (TensorFlow) (PyTorch) (Transformers) (Elastic Stack) (Keras) (Docker) (Rasa) (Bash) (Git) (CUDA) (Parallel Programming) Matlab SQL | LaTex Java